Okay, so while the United States was
going hog wild on industrialization
during the guilded age, that has some
pretty momentous consequences for how
the working class lived and worked and
got paid and how they formed labor
unions to improve their lives. And I
reckon it's time to talk about it. So,
if you're ready to get them brain cows
milked, let's get to it. Okay, now the
first thing you need to know about labor
in the guilded age is that
industrialization created the occasion
for a massive expansion of the
workforce. In other words,
industrialization created a metric
buttload of new jobs, and that meant
that a corresponding metric buttload of
workers took those jobs. Like between
1865 and 1898, the industrial workforce
tripled, and two groups in particular
were responsible for that increase. Oh,
and by the way, if you want note guys to
follow along with this video and all my
videos, check that link in the
description. Okay, so first you had
rural farmers migrating to industrial
cities to find jobs. And why exactly
were the farmers moving to cities, says
you? Well, says I. If you'll think back
to the beginning of this unit, you'll
remember that one of the main
developments during this period was the
commercialization of agriculture. Which
is to say, independent family farms were
being gobbled up by huge agricultural
corporations. And that meant that these
farmers needed jobs quick, fast, and in
a hurry. And as it turned out, they
found those jobs in big industrial
cities like New York and Chicago. And
then the second group that expanded the
industrial workforce during the guilded
age was immigrants from Europe and Asia.
And since the next video is exclusively
about this group, I'll save that juicy
tale for later. And then the third group
that added to the workforce was women
and children. Now in terms of women,
they were generally young and single.
And maybe you're thinking, "Wow, these
industrialists were so progressive and
great champions of the women folk who
had been up to this point socially
marginalized among Americans." But
here's where I tell you that the owners
of these corporations weren't exactly
feminists. No. Despite the fact that
over the last decades of the 19th
century, women became a vital labor
supply for American industries. They got
paid about 25% less than their male
counterparts doing the same work. So
hiring a woman was a real nice bargain
because they did the same work for a lot
less pay and that extra pocket cheddar
went straight to the business owner. But
then children also entered the workforce
in large numbers as well. In fact, by
the end of the 19th century, almost 2
million children under the age of 16
worked across various industries. But
why were children working in the first
place? Like didn't they have to go to
school or something? Well, no.
Compulsory schooling laws didn't come
until later. And do you remember all
those farmers that I mentioned earlier
who were moving to cities and looking
for jobs? Yeah. They brought their kids
with them. And it was a pretty common
thing for kids to work with their
parents on the farm. And so when these
families arrived in the city, these kids
did what they did on the farm, which is
to say they found work. But there was a
big difference between farm work and
industrial work. Not only were the
children working apart from their
families, but their jobs were uh real
dangerous. Like coal mines employed
young boys under the age of 10 to sort
through piles of debris to find any
unprocessed coal that was missed by the
adult miners. And factory owners liked
employing children because they were
small and therefore useful for fitting
into small spaces and repairing
machinery. But don't worry, even though
it was common for working children to
lose fingers or get the black lung or
straight up die, at least they got paid
less than women for their trouble. Okay,
now despite the hardships of the working
class, they did on the whole make more
money than did the industrial workers in
the middle of the century. In fact, by
the 1880s, the real wages of industrial
workers rose by about 20%. And real
wages, by the way, refer to the actual
purchasing power of money by removing
the effects of inflation. The point is,
by all measures, wages for American
workers were increasing and therefore
wealth was spreading to the working
class. But even though that was true, it
was simultaneously true that the wealth
gap between the richest Americans and
the poorest was growing real fast. For
example, by 1890, about 90% of working
Americans earned an average of $500 a
year, so a little more than $40 per
month. By contrast, John D. Rockefeller
at the height of his business empire was
making about $700 an hour. So on the
whole, 1% of the wealthiest Americans
during this period controlled about a
third of the nation's wealth and the
wealthiest 10% of Americans controlled
about 3/4ers of the nation's wealth. And
so those wealthy tycoons at the top and
the members of the burgeoning middle
class gave rise to a new economic
phenomenon, namely conspicuous
consumption, which is to say they bought
expensive stuff to put their status on
display, which also indicated a growing
level of class consciousness. And a good
example of how the wealthiest Americans
did this was the construction of the
largest private residence in the nation.
Completed in 1895, namely the Builtmore
House. Now, this incredible structure
boasts over 175,000 square ft of floor
space, 35 bedrooms, and 43 bathrooms,
which, if I'm being honest, is too many
bathrooms. I mean, where I come from,
you don't need any more than 42
bathrooms to live comfortably. And then
the middle class reached into their
pockets and found plenty of expendable
income. So, they got in on the
conspicuous consumption party as well.
And this increased wealth can be
demonstrated with the rise of mail
orderer cataloges that offered their
customers dizzying amounts of industrial
products that customers could order from
their homes. For example, this Sears
Robuck and Company catalog from 1898 has
over a thousand pages filled with
products for order from food to medicine
to furniture to tools to obesity
powders. And I don't know exactly what
an obesity powder is, but apparently if
you don't order it, the result is sudden
death. So that's fun. The point is,
while the middle class didn't have
nearly as much money as the top level
industrialists, they had enough money
that they could buy many of the
trappings of wealth and put it on
display for all to see. Now, over on the
other side of the tracks, many people
lived in poverty. Wages were well below
what would be considered a comfortable
standard of living, and the working
class suffered in the waves of economic
turmoil. For example, as a result of the
panic of 1873 and the panic of 1893, the
wealthy classes were pretty well
insulated, but the working class found
their wages dropping precipitously.
Okay, so probably the most important
development regarding labor during this
period was the growth and multiplication
of labor unions. Now, by definition, a
labor union is an organization made up
of workers who use collective bargaining
to negotiate better working conditions
and wages. And the idea is that a large
group of workers is more persuasive than
individual workers and can therefore use
their collective voice to advocate for
themselves. Now, here's where I tell you
that the wealthy industrialists all seem
to hold a worldview that assumed that
their interest and the interest of their
workers were the same. Therefore, it was
the responsibility of the company owner
to set wages and create policies that
kept the workforce happy. After all, it
was the industrialists who had all the
money and owned all the machinery. And
that success indicated to them that they
were best able to make decisions. And in
light of that, these elite
industrialists often refused on
principle to negotiate with workers who
joined together and tried to change
company policy. And side note, it's
worth a minor chuckle that the
industrialists were giddy about banding
together in order to eliminate
competition from the market, but
considered negotiations with collectives
of workers to be immoral and a slight to
their own judgment. Anyway, this growing
disparity between the wealthy and the
working class and workers increasing
disagreement with all power being
concentrated in their boss' hands
ultimately led to discontent among the
laborers whose main form of resistance
was to create labor unions. Now, I need
to introduce you to one of the most
significant unions of the guilded age,
namely the Knights of Labor. And it was
founded on the premise that the
interests of workers and corporate
capitalists were not in fact the same.
And by 1885, the Knights of Labor had
over a million members across the United
States. And its membership was pretty
diverse, including black workers and
women and immigrants, although not
Chinese immigrants, because hey, it's
still the Gilded Age. Let's not get
crazy. But it was still an admirable
amount of diversity, especially when you
compare it to a union like the American
Federation of Labor, which restricted
its membership to skilled white men.
Anyway, the Knights led their members to
advocate for an 8-hour workday and the
abolition of child labor and higher
wages among many other reforms. But
despite their early successes, the
Knights of Labor encountered a major
blow as the result of growing internal
division and the disastrous Hey Market
riot of 1886. And here's what happened.
So, workers in Chicago had gathered in
Hey Market Square to protest police
violence during a worker strike that had
occurred earlier that month. And as it
happened, a group of anarchists who
advocated a violent overthrow of
capitalist systems were in the crowd,
though they were not associated with the
Knights of Labor. And when the police
tried to disperse the crowds, a bomb
went off, and the police responded by
firing their guns into the crowd. And by
the end, seven police officers and four
protesters were dead. Now, it was
unclear exactly who ignited the bomb,
and much of the evidence pointed to the
anarchists in the crowd. But those wy
industrial capitalists were quick to
blame the Knights of Labor and use this
incident to show how violent and
dangerous labor unions can be. Dirty
move, but ultimately very effective.
Anyway, this is the narrative that took
hold and by 1890, the Knights of Labor
membership had dropped precipitously to
20,000 members. But then a second
example of laborers using collective
action to better their working
conditions occurred in the Pullman
strike of 1894. So George Pullman was a
railroad tycoon who specialized in
manufacturing luxury sleeping cars for
trains. And as a result of the panic of
1893, Pullman cut his workers wages
drastically and they responded by
organizing a strike and then later a
boycott of trains carrying Pullman cars.
But ultimately the strike was broken by
the federal government under the
leadership of President Grover
Cleveland. You see, because these trains
also carried the US mail, Cleveland was
able to justify deploying US troops to
break the Pullman strike. And it's a
perfect example of the attitude of the
federal government toward industrial
capitalists during this period. In
general, the government opposed very
little restriction or control over the
expansion of their businesses and
wealth. But when workers opposed these
corporations, the government mostly
sided with the corporations, which in
some cases meant sending the actual US
military to shut down labor strikes. All
right, click here to watch my other
videos from unit 6. And you can click
here to grab my video note guides, which
are going to help you get all the
contents of this course firmly crammed
into your brain fold. I'm glad you came
around and I'll catch you on the
flip-flop.